Guide to the Anspach Travel Bureau Collection of Tourism Literature, 1942-2000 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anspach Travel Bureau Collection of Tourism Literature 1942-2000 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anspach Travel Bureau
12.0 linear feet Extent: 2,000 Items
Real estate and travel company founded in 1932 by brothers Herman and Robert Anspach in Highland Park, Ill. Currently part of Valerie Wilson Travel, Inc. Collection spans 1942-2000 with the bulk of materials dating from the 1960s-1980s. Primarily brochures, leaflets and other take-away direct marketing materials advertising resorts, hotels, airlines, cruise lines, and other services and destinations comprising the travel and tourism industry. Also includes newsletters, itineraries, and some correspondence. All continents and ocean regions are represented. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00045
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Anspach Travel Bureau Collection of Tourism Literature were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Collection Overview
Collection spans 1942-2000 with the bulk of materials dating from the 1960s-1980s. Primarily brochures, leaflets and other take-away direct marketing materials advertising resorts, hotels, airlines, cruise lines, and other services and destinations comprising the travel and tourism industry. Also includes newsletters, itineraries, and some correspondence. All continents and ocean regions are represented.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by region.
Subject Headings
Anspach Travel Bureau; Advertising -- Hotels; Advertising -- Tourism; Cruise lines; Direct marketing; Hotels; Resorts; Travel; Travel agents -- Illinois; Travel agents -- United States; Illinois; Brochures; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related material can be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Advertising Ephemera Collection
Charles McKinney Papers
Henry Haberman Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company Account Files
J. Walter Thompson Company Chicago Office Non-Proprietary Research Reports
J. Walter Thompson Company Corporation Vertical Files
J. Walter Thompson Company Eleanor Newman Papers
J. Walter Thompson Company New Business Records
Jacqueline End Papers
Wunderman Archives
Detailed Description of Collection
- General Files, 1971-1987 and undated
  - Capers Club, 1971-1987 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Cesia Travel Service, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Club Med, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Cruises, 1966-1975 and undated (Box 1)
  - Joseph Edmund, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Lindblad Explorer, 1981-1983 and undated (Box 1)
  - Northwest Orient Tours, undated (Box 1)
  - Society Expeditions, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Swan Hellenic, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - William D. Buckman's Travel Time, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Africa, 1964-1985 and undated (Box 1)
  - Africa/Antarctica, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Egypt, 1981-1984 and undated (Box 2)
  - Ethiopa, 1966-1974 (Box 2)
  - General, 1963-1985, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Kenya, 1973-1985 and undated (Box 2)
  - Morocco, 1965-1974 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Senegal, 1970 and undated (Box 2)
  - South Africa, 1964-1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Tanzania, 1965 and undated (Box 3)
  - Zambia, 1982 and undated (Box 3)
- Asia, 1957-1985 and undated (Box 3)
  - Bhutan, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Burma, 1959-1981 (Box 3)
  - Cambodia, undated (Box 3)
  - China (Box 3)
    - Cities, undated (Box 3)
    - General, 1979-1984 and undated (Box 3)
    - Provinces and regions, 1984 and undated (Box 3)
    - Sights, undated (Box 3)
    - General, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
  - Hong Kong, 1967-1982 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - India (Box 4)
    - Cities--Delhi, 1958-1968 (Box 4)
    - Cities--Other, 1957 and undated (Box 4)
    - General (includes Nepal, Sri Lanka, Bhutan), 1957-1984 and undated (Box 4)
    - Hotels and maps, 1966-1975 and undated (Box 4)
    - Regions and sights, 1957-1975 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Tourism and travel agent materials, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Indonesia (Box 5)
    - General, 1966-1976 (Box 5)
    - Irian Jaya, circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - Java, 1981 and undated (Box 5)
  - Israel, 1942-1984 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Japan (Box 5)
    - ADA Handbook, Japan and Hong Kong, 1969 (Box 5)
    - General, 1957-1975 and undated (Box 5)
    - Hotels, 1957-1975 and undated (Box 6)
    - Maps, 1957-1975 and undated (Box 6)
    - Sightseeing, 1957-1975 and undated (Box 6)
  - Korea, 1957-1981 (Box 6)
  - Malaysia, 1969 and undated (Box 6)
  - Nepal/Tibet/Himalaya, 1967-1982 (Box 6)
  - Pakistan/Iran/Turkey, undated (Box 6)
  - Singapore, 1969-1981 and undated (Box 6)
  - Sri Lanka (Ceylon), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 6)
  - Taiwan (Formosa), 1960-1973 (Box 7)
  - Thailand, 1969-1981, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Yemen, 1984 (Box 7)
- Canada (Box 7)
  - General, 1968-1976 (Box 7)
- Caribbean, 1947-1985 and undated (Box 7)
  - Antigua, 1965-1976 and undated (Box 7)
  - Aruba, 1965-1968 and undated (Box 7)
  - Bahamas (Box 7)
    - General, 1966-1979 and undated (Box 7)
    - Hotels and sights, 1965-1980 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Barbados, 1962-1972 and undated (Box 8)
  - Bermuda, 1964-1980 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Bonaire, 1957-1982 (Box 8)
  - Cayman Islands, 1967-1982 and undated (Box 8)
  - Dominican Republic, 1974-1976 and undated (Box 8)
  - General, 1947-1983 (Box 8)
  - Grenada, 1961-1971 (Box 8)
  - Guadeloupe, 1969 and undated (Box 8)
  - Haiti, circa 1965-1975 (Box 8)
  - Jamaica, 1961-1974 and undated, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Jamaica, 1961-1974 and undated, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Martinique, 1968-1980 and undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous islands (includes Curaçao, Dominica, Nevis, St. Vincent Grenadines, Turks and Caicos), 1967-1972 and undated (Box 9)
  - Puerto Rico, 1962-1975 and undated (Box 9)
  - St. Lucia, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
  - St. Martin, 1974-1979 (Box 9)
  - Sint Maartin, 1970-1980 and undated (Box 9)
  - Trinidad/Tobago, 1958-1971 and undated (Box 9)
  - Virgin Islands (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1975 and undated (Box 9)
    - St. Croix, 1962-1973 and undated (Box 9)
    - St. Thomas, 1963-1975 and undated (Box 10)
    - Tortola, 1969 and undated (Box 10)
    - Virgin Gorda, 1972-1985 and undated (Box 10)
- Central America, 1958-2000 and undated (Box 10)
  - Belize, undated (Box 10)
  - Costa Rica/El Salvador, 1969 and undated (Box 10)
  - General, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Guatemala (Box 10)
    - Dale Nichols, Magnificent Mystery: Tikal, and The Mayan Mystery, 1970, 1973 (Box 10)
    - General, 1958-1977 and undated (Box 10)
  - Honduras, 1996-2000 (Box 10)
  - Nicaragua, undated (Box 10)
  - Panama, 1964-1997, (2 folders) (Box 10)
- Europe, 1958-1984 and undated (Box 10)
  - Belgium, 1975 and undated (Box 11)
  - England/Great Britain, 1977-1984 and undated (Box 11)
  - France, 1977 and undated (Box 11)
    - General, 1979-1982 (Box 11)
    - General--Car rentals, 1983 (Box 11)
    - Tours and cruises, 1975-1984 (Box 11)
  - Greece (Box 11)
    - Athens, 1963-1970 and undated (Box 11)
    - Corfu, 1963-1981 and undated (Box 11)
    - Cruises, 1983-1984 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1956-1973 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Rhodes, 1963-1969 and undated (Box 12)
  - Holland/Netherlands, 1959-1974 and undated (Box 12)
  - Hungary, 1969-1973 and undated (Box 12)
  - Ireland, 1967-1981 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Italy (Box 12)
    - Costa Smeralda/Sardegna (Sardinia), 1967-1977 and undated (Box 12)
    - Dolomites/Dolomiti, 1970 and undated (Box 12)
    - Florence/Firenze, 1965-1982 and undated (Box 12)
    - Lago di Como, 1966-1973 and undated (Box 12)
    - Lago di Gardia/Sirmione, 1970-1981 and undated (Box 12)
    - Lago Maggiore/Stresa, 1959-1981 and undated (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Portofino, undated (Box 13)
    - Positano, 1973 and undated (Box 13)
    - Riviera, undated (Box 13)
    - Rome/Roma, 1958-1982 and undated (Box 13)
    - Santa Margherita Ligure/Golfo Tigullo, 1967-1981 and undated (Box 13)
    - Sicily, 1957-1983 and undated (Box 13)
    - Venice/Venezia, 1967-1982 and undated (Box 13)
  - Malta, 1978 (Box 13)
  - Portugal (Box 13)
    - Algarve, 1966-1973 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Estoril, 1962-1973 and undated (Box 14)
    - Lisbon/Lisboa, 1963-1974 and undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1984 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Russia/USSR (Moscow), undated (Box 14)
  - Scandinavia (Box 14)
    - Denmark, 1959-1982 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Finland, 1972-1976 and undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1981 and undated (Box 14)
    - Norway, 1960-1981 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Sweden, 1967-1981 (Box 15)
  - Scotland, 1974-1977 and undated (Box 15)
  - Spain (Box 15)
    - Barcelona, 1967-1974 and undated (Box 15)
    - Canary/Balearic/Madeira islands, 1964-1972 and undated (Box 15)
    - Costa del Sol (Box 15)
      - Malaga/Torremolinos, 1964-1972 (Box 15)
      - Marbella, 1966-1982 and undated (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970 and undated (Box 15)
      - Sotogrande, 1965-1971 and undated (Box 15)
    - Gaudí, 1968 and undated (Box 15)
    - Madrid, 1963-1980 (Box 15)
    - Mallorca/Majorca, 1960-1974 and undated (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1960-1982 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Paradores, 1964 and undated (Box 16)
    - Spain/Portugal, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Switzerland (Box 16)
    - Grindelwald, 1969 and undated (Box 16)
    - Interlaken/Victoria/Jungfrau, 1967-1970 and undated (Box 16)
    - Lausanne, 1970 and undated (Box 16)
    - Lucerne, 1970 and undated (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1979 and undated (Box 16)
    - Montreux/Vevey, 1960-1970 and undated (Box 17)
    - Zurich, 1977 and undated (Box 17)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 17)
    - Dubrovnik/Croatia, 1962-1983 and undated (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Montenegro, 1972-1983 and undated (Box 17)
- Mexico, 1966-1982 and undated (Box 17)
  - Acapulco, 1966-1975 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Baja California, 1971-1976 and undated (Box 17)
  - Cancun, 1975-1980 and undated (Box 17)
  - Guadalajara, 1967-1973 and undated (Box 18)
  - Ixtapa/Zihuatanejo, 1979 and undated (Box 18)
  - Manzanillo, undated (Box 18)
  - Mazatlan, 1969-1975 and undated (Box 18)
  - Mexico City, 1966-1973 and undated (Box 18)
  - Michoacan, 1966 and undated (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1967-1973 and undated (Box 18)
  - Morelos, undated (Box 18)
  - Puerto Vallarta, 1969-1982 and undated (Box 18)
  - Quintana Roo (includes Cozumel, Isla Mujeres), 1969-1975 and undated (Box 18)
  - Yucatan, 1967-1977 and undated (Box 18)
- Pacific Region, 1950s-1984 and undated (Box 18)
  - Australia (Box 18)
    - General, 1964-1973 (Box 19)
    - Great Barrier Reef/Cairns, 1960s-1973 and undated (Box 19)
    - Maps, undated (Box 19)
    - Sights and hotels, 1964-1973 and undated (Box 19)
  - Easter Island, 1974-1975 (Box 19)
  - Fiji, 1965-1972 and undated (Box 19)
  - Galapagos, 1968-1984 and undated (Box 19)
  - Hawaii (Box 19)
    - General, 1950s-1975 (Box 19)
    - Hawaii (Big Island), 1967-1983 and undated (Box 19)
    - Kauai, 1962-1981 and undated (Box 20)
    - Lanai/Molokai, 1975 and undated (Box 20)
    - Maui, 1962-1983 and undated (Box 20)
    - Oahu, 1960-1981 and undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous island reports, undated (Box 20)
  - New Zeal and, 1960-1973 and undated (Box 20)
  - Norfolk Island/Melanesia, undated (Box 20)
  - Papua/New Guinea, 1971-1981 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Samoa (American and Western), 1966-1972 and undated (Box 20)
    - South Pacific Islands (includes Laulasi, Micronesia, New Hebrides, Rabaul, Solomon Islands), 1969-1972 and undated (Box 21)
    - Tahiti/Bora Bora, 1964-1977 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 21)
- South America1950s-1981 and undated (Box 21)
  - Argentina, 1960 and undated (Box 21)
  - Brazil, 1950s-1977 and undated (Box 21)
  - Chile, 1957-1972 and undated (Box 21)
  - Colombia, 1966-1970 and undated (Box 21)
  - Ecuador, 1967-1978 and undated (Box 21)
    - Maps, 1956-1966 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous tours, 1966-1981 and undated (Box 22)
  - Peru, 1958-1974 and undated (Box 22)
  - Various countries (includes Bolivia, British Guiana, Surinam, Uruguay), 1973 and undated (Box 22)
- United States1958-1983 and undated (Box 22)
  - Colorado, 1966-1971 and undated (Box 22)
  - Florida (Box 22)
    - Boca Raton, 1980 and undated (Box 22)
    - Fort Lauderdale, 1972-1974 and undated (Box 22)
    - Keys, 1969-1973 and undated (Box 22)
    - Miami, 1964-1976 and undated (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1982 and undated (Box 22)
    - Palm Beach, 1958-1972 and undated (Box 22)
    - Pompano Beach, 1972-1983 and undated (Box 23)
    - Port St. Lucie, 1965-1971 (Box 23)
    - St. Petersburg, 1972-1974 (Box 23)
    - Sanibel Beach, 1974 and undated (Box 23)
    - Sarasota, 1965-1974 and undated (Box 23)
  - Louisiana--New Orleans, 1963 and undated (Box 23)
  - Michigan, 1965-1981 and undated (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous A-Z, 1966-1983 and undated (Box 23)
  - Missouri, 1963-1966 (Box 23)
  - Nevada, 1969-1974 and undated (Box 23)
  - New Mexico, 1971-1977 and undated (Box 23)
  - South Carolina, 1970-1983 and undated (Box 23)
  - Vermont, 1972-1977 (Box 23)
  - Virginia, 1964-1975 and undated (Box 23)
  - Wyoming, 1970-1977 (Box 23)
  - Wisconsin, 1962-1966 and undated (Box 23)